everyone welcome again in this Tasker
session I am going to talk about how you
can scan and verify different elements
on a PDF document now we have already
seen how you can compare two different
PDFs and get a generic report on whether
the comparison was successful depending
on your accuracy percentage which you
have specified for that particular
comparison but if you want to make a
more in detail verification of each
element on your PDF and whether it is
matching up to the expected requirements
then we have to use the PDF scan which
is provided in the PDF engine
and let's look at how does it work okay
so we are going to use the same PDF
which we have used for our comparison it
is generated by one of the transient
sample applications which is the vehicle
insurance application and once you go
through the whole different screens then
you will find that it will generate this
particular code based on your choices
you have made okay
and there are different sections to it
so we can also verify different elements
on this particular PDF okay so let's see
uh how you can scan this particular PDF
and then how you can also make some
verifications on different elements
so to scan uh we have created a module
uh folder inside our modules which is
PDF scan okay and then right click and
then go to scan instead of application
uh we have to select PDF okay so
application will cover any desktop or
web application uh but PDF will
basically scan your PDF documents okay
so select this PDF
and after this we need to provide a path
for or we have to select the particular
PDF document which we want to scan okay
in this case I want to scan this
particular document
so I will open this in my PDF scan and
this is the window which is the PDF scan
okay now it has got different uh menu
items which we'll discuss
but it also provides you a preview of
your PDF document okay so I have got
just one page
if you have got multiple Pages it will
show you the preview of multiple pages
okay
um I can fit this particular PDF to the
screen by using this Zoom fit option I
can also zoom in and zoom out using this
Zoom toolbar okay
foreign
items are select document language now I
can select this particular PDF document
in different languages okay and then um
there is also a show content preview
uh which may be hidden by default but
you can always change it to show and
hide this content preview so whenever
you scan any particular element uh the
value of it or the preview of it will be
shown in this particular window okay I
can always close this particular PDF
scan window from here and I can also
scan a new document once I am finished
with this particular document using this
particular option
then there is save option to save all
the controls which you have scanned and
then there are three options to
basically scan three different elements
on the PDF okay so the first is a text
option second is the image option and
the third is the table option so these
are the three main elements which you'll
find in any PDF document and that is why
these three types of scanned elements
are present in your PDF scan okay so
let's see one by one how we can scan
these three different elements okay
so when you click on any of these three
uh menu items your cursor will change to
a plus sign and it will allow you to
select a particular uh area for your
element okay so based on that content AI
it will scan that particular element and
it will show you also a view of it in
the content view right and then uh when
you do the verification it will compare
it based on that particular scanned area
okay
so say for example I want to verify the
make of the vehicle okay so that's
present under vehicle data and that's
the value called Audi so I'm going to
scan this particular area
now I can Define the scan area depending
on my requirements
um so if there are options which are
much larger than this particular option
then you can scan a larger area as well
okay
so once you scan that particular text on
the right hand side you will see that it
will show you a type which is a text
type and then a name of generic name
which you can always edit okay
so double click on this and you will be
able to rename this so I will rename
this to uh make okay and uh
I can always jump back to that scanned
area okay
and you will see this will be
highlighted whenever I click on this so
it is jump to this area
I can always redraw this particular
option okay so using this option I can
redraw this particular element so
basically modify this whole element
together right
so this is how you can if you have
scanned earlier and you want to change
it you can do that or I can completely
remove this particular scan okay so it
will be removed from this particular
scan document
so if I go again here and this time
around if I select a fuel type S which
is diesel right so I can rename this to
fuel type
and then in the content view you will
also see uh what's the value of that
particular text okay so it will
basically show you a preview of what you
have scanned so it is a text type and
the value is diesel so that's what is
shown in the content View
so that's how you can scan any
particular text in this uh in this PDF
document okay and you can store this as
a control so when we save this it will
be saved as a control uh in our module
okay which we will see later you can use
it for any verification or anything in
your test case right
now coming to uh image based uh scanning
so in image we can scan this logo which
is the tricentis logo right on this
particular PDF document
uh just to verify that this logo appears
on this document or not right so
similarly if you there are other images
you can scan them again it will show as
a type as image right and I can always
rename
I can always rename this to uh the
proper naming conventions so I'll name
it as logo
right
so we have got two types of elements one
is text one is image and these are the
two controls the third type is table now
ideally if you have got a proper table
in your PDF document you can scan this
but even if you don't have uh and this
you still want to scan
um this particular area as a table you
can still do it it may not work
perfectly or because as you can see the
rows and columns are not aligned
properly so Tosca cannot identify which
are the rows and which are the columns
here right so you need to have a proper
table uh in your PDF document so that
Tosca can identify that and there are
few things which you can do here okay so
you can Define uh whether you want to
use a header column or you want to use
the header row you can Define which
particular row you want to use as your
header row right so generally it is the
first row and that's where by default it
will select the first row but you can
always change it similarly you can use
the column as the header column as well
if you want okay depends on what kind of
data is present in that table
so as you can see uh I don't have proper
header rows here and the values are
selected as the header row and that's
where I said that you should have proper
uh
proper alignment of your rows and
columns if you are scanning a particular
table okay
also you can adjust the cell borders
here if they are not adjusted properly
in the view okay
you can see here when I uh over over
this it will also show the coordinates
here right
um also if there are any invisible cells
you can also select this option to
consider invisible cells right but uh
generally speaking uh this is not an
ideal table to be selected but anyways
let's have this as a control and we will
see how it looks like when we save this
particular module okay
so now as you can see I have got three
control types one is text one is image
and one is stable
um I can always redraw them or I can
always jump to these different controls
on my PDF document to verify whether
they are
exactly the same when I scan them I can
also remove them from my control or my
PDF document okay
so these are the things we can do uh
after this I can go ahead and save this
and I can close this PDF scan okay so
that's how you can scan your PDF
document and once you do that uh you
will see there are different controls
which are created here right
uh it will take the path as the name of
the PDF document but you can always
change it back right so this is the
insurance code so I will name it
Insurance code PDF
right and there are different controls
created based on what we have scanned
right so one is the fuel tab which is
the text type uh one is the logo which
is the image control and one is the
table right
also there are two other uh module
properties one is Target PDF and the PDF
password so when you use this module in
a test case which we are going to do you
will see that you can provide a PDF
password and then you have to provide
the PDF path here okay
so let's create a new test case folder
here called PDF scan
and let's uh
create a test case here verify
Insurance code
okay and then I am going to search and
add step
and I'm going to search for insurance
code PDF
okay once you select this module you
will see all the different controls
which are present here right so here I
need to provide the target PDF so which
I want to run
so this is my target PDF and I'm going
to put the name here
okay
dot PDF
I don't have a PDF password so I don't
need to provide it uh fuel type right
so the value will always be present here
but if you think it's a different value
as per the requirement you can
write it down here
and it will automatically select the
action mode as verify because that's
what you want to do in a PDF right so
you want to verify whether the text
which is which we have scanned has this
particular value okay
and then uh in logo
uh what we can do is we can say exists
right and equals equals true
so that's the verification we can do uh
for uh image type right so we can say
exist exist equal equal true right
so that will perform uh the verification
on the image
now coming to the verification of the
table uh we have got rows and cells okay
and you can select any particular row or
column and then you can select any
particular cells so in the column you
can see we have got all the values like
product data start date Insurance
um and cutsy car right so in order to
put a verification on a particular table
we can select a particular column so
first let's see what's there in this
particular PDF okay and what we want to
verify so this is the table we had
selected so if I want to verify whether
this bonus one is displayed under this
particular column right which is the
second column
so how you can do that is you have to go
to the column and then you have to
select this particular column number and
you have to enter it right so I want to
select the second column and then I want
to select a particular cell inside this
which is the first cell okay and here I
want to verify the value which is called
bonus one but there is also some other a
value like meditating right but if I
want to put a regular expression kind of
thing here and just put bonus one that
is what I want to verify no matter what
other values are present I don't want to
verify those so I'll put star and star
at the beginning and end so that
whatever text is of before this and
after this won't matter but it will just
check for this bonus one okay
so you can verify all the different
values in this columns using this way
okay you can choose the column number
and then you can choose the cell number
and then just put the value you want to
verify within the table
okay so this is how you can put a
verification for your table values
and then let's go ahead and execute this
okay and let's see whether it works as
expected or not
so as you can see uh our test case has
passed now Okay so
we have got all three verifications
which we wanted on the PDF document you
can see them in the log info so
the text verification was successful
expected and actual values are same the
image verification was successful
because the image exists in the PDF and
the table verification was also
successful so
the particular value in the column
matches with what we have provided okay
so you can see I have used regular
expression and even though it is
meditating a before bonus one it is
still able to compare these two
particular values
okay so you can use regular expression
wherever you feel that you have a
particular text which remain constant
but others can change okay so
that's how you can verify different
elements on your PDF document and that's
all uh you have got in the PDF engine
for Tosca through which you can scan
different elements and then you can use
it as a module in your test cases and
then put a necessary verifications so
that you can verify your PDF which is
generated from the web application so it
will help you to cover end to end test
case where you perform your automation
on the web application and once the PDF
is generated and stored somewhere you
can directly access it and then put your
verifications through a test case so
that it is a complete end-to-end test
case verification right
so hope this session was useful for you
in order to understand how you can scan
and verify different elements on any
particular PDF document
if you have got any questions please
leave them in the comments and do look
out for more interesting videos which
are coming up in the next few days